The Canine Caper of the Century
One Hundred and One Dalmatians is a adventure, animation,
comedy film directed by Wolfgang Reitherman.
When a litter of dalmatian puppies are abducted by the minions of Cruella De Vil, the
parents must find them before she uses them for a diabolical fashion statement.
Pongo (voice), played by Rod Taylor.
Colonel / Jasper (voice), played by J. Pat O'Malley.
Cruella De Vil / Miss Birdwell (voice), played by Betty Lou Gerson.
Nanny / Queenie / Lucy (voice), played by Martha Wentworth.
Roger (voice), played by Ben Wright.
Perdita (voice), played by Cate Bauer.
One Hundred and One Dalmatians (also known as 101 Dalmatians) is a 1961 American animated adventure comedy
film produced by Walt Disney Productions with distribution by Buena Vista Distribution.
Adapted from Dodie Smith's 1956 novel The Hundred and One Dalmatians, the film was directed by Hamilton Luske, Clyde
Geronimi, and Wolfgang Reitherman in his feature-length directorial debut, from a script by Bill Peet.
It features the voice talents of Rod Taylor, J.
Pat O'Malley, Betty Lou Gerson, Martha Wentworth, Ben Wright,
Cate Bauer, Dave Frankham, and Fred Worlock.
The film's plot follows Pongo and Perdita, two London-based Dalmatians who give birth to a litter of fifteen puppies,
who are later kidnapped by the obsessive socialite Cruella de Vil, wanting to make their fur into coats.
Pongo and Perdita set out on a cross-country rescue mission
to save the litter from the maniacal Cruella.
They rescue 84 additional Dalmatians in the process, bringing the total to 101.
One Hundred and One Dalmatians was released in theaters on January 25, 1961, to positive reviews from critics
and was a box-office success, grossing $14 million domestically in its original theatrical run.
It became the first animated feature to earn over $10 million during its initial release, and became the eighth-highest-grossing film of
the year in the North American box office and the highest-grossing animated film when reissues of films are not counted.
Aside from its box-office revenue, the employment of inexpensive animation techniques, such as using xerography
during the process of inking and painting traditional animation cels, kept production costs down.
Counting reissues, the film grossed $303 million worldwide, and when adjusted for inflation, is the twelfth-highest-grossing film in the North American box office and the
second-highest-grossing animated film globally, as well as being the highest-selling traditionally animated film of all time at an estimate of over 199,800,000 sold tickets.
The success of the film made Disney expand it into a media franchise, with a
live-action remake released in 1996, followed by a sequel in 2000.
A direct-to-video animated sequel to the 1961 film, 101 Dalmatians
II: Patch's London Adventure, was released in 2003.
Two animated television series based on the franchise were also produced, with 101
Dalmatians: The Series in 1997 and 101 Dalmatian Street in 2019.
A live-action reboot, Cruella, was released in 2021.
The film explores themes of london, england, cartoon, villain, puppy, dog.
The tone is lighthearted.